<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix id="svn.webdav">
  <!-- @ENGLISH {{{
  <title>WebDAV and Autoversioning</title>
  @ENGLISH }}} -->
  <title>WebDAV и автоматическое управление версиями</title>
  <!-- See also svn.preface.organization -->

  <simplesect>

    <para>WebDAV is an extension to HTTP, and is growing more and more
      popular as a standard for file-sharing.  Today's operating
      systems are becoming extremely Web-aware, and many now have
      built-in support for mounting <quote>shares</quote> exported by
      WebDAV servers.</para>

    <para>If you use Apache/mod_dav_svn as your Subversion network
      server, then to some extent, you are also running a WebDAV
      server.  This appendix gives some background on the nature of
      this protocol, how Subversion uses it, and how well Subversion
      interoperates with other software that is WebDAV-aware.</para>

  </simplesect>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.webdav.basic">
    <title>Basic WebDAV Concepts</title>

    <para>This section provides a very brief, very general overview to
      the ideas behind WebDAV.  It should lay the foundation for
      understanding WebDAV compatibility issues between clients and
      servers.</para>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.webdav.basic.original">
      <title>Original WebDAV</title>

      <para>RFC 2518 defines a set of concepts and accompanying
        extension methods to HTTP 1.1 that make the web into a more
        universal read/write medium.  The basic idea is that a
        WebDAV-compliant web server can act like a generic file
        server; clients can mount shared folders that behave much like
        NFS or SMB filesystems.</para>

      <para>The tragedy, though, is that the RFC 2518 WebDAV
        specification does not provide any sort of model for version
        control, despite the <quote>V</quote> in DAV.  Basic WebDAV
        clients and servers assume only one version of each file or
        directory exists, and can be repeatedly overwritten.</para>

      <para>Here are the concepts and terms introduced in basic
        WebDAV:</para>

      <variablelist>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Resources</term>
          <listitem>
            <para> WebDAV lingo refers to any server-side object
              (that can be described with a URI) as a
              <firstterm>resource</firstterm>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>New write methods</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Beyond the standard HTTP <literal>PUT</literal>
              method (which creates or overwrites a web resource),
              WebDAV defines new <literal>COPY</literal> and
              <literal>MOVE</literal> methods for duplicating or
              rearranging resources.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Collections</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A <firstterm>collection</firstterm> is the WebDAV
              term for a grouping of resources.  In most cases, it
              is analogous to a directory.  Whereas file resources
              can be written or created with a
              <literal>PUT</literal> method, collection resources
              are created with the new <literal>MKCOL</literal>
              method.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Properties</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This is the same idea present in
              Subversion&mdash;metadata attached to files and
              collections.  A client can list or retrieve properties
              attached to a resource with the new
              <literal>PROPFIND</literal> method, and can change
              them with the <literal>PROPPATCH</literal> method.
              Some properties are wholly created and controlled by
              users (e.g. a property called <quote>color</quote>),
              and others are wholly created and controlled by the
              WebDAV server (e.g. a property that contains the last
              modification time of a file).  The former kind are
              called <firstterm>dead properties</firstterm>, and the
              latter kind are called <firstterm>live
                properties</firstterm>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Locking</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A WebDAV server may decide to offer a locking
              feature to clients&mdash;this part of the
              specification is optional, although most WebDAV
              servers do offer the feature.  If present, then
              clients can use the new <literal>LOCK</literal> and
              <literal>UNLOCK</literal> methods to mediate access to
              a resource.  In most cases these methods are used to
              create exclusive write locks (as discussed in <xref
                linkend="svn.basic.vsn-models.lock-unlock"/>), although shared write
              locks are also possible in some server
              implementations.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Access control</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A more recent specification (RFC 3744) defines a
              system for defining access control lists (ACLs) on
              WebDAV resources.  Some clients and servers have begun
              to implement this feature.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.webdav.basic.deltav">
      <title>DeltaV Extensions</title>

      <para>Because RFC 2518 left out versioning concepts, another
        committee was left with the responsibility of writing RFC
        3253, which adds versioning to WebDAV,
        a.k.a. <quote>DeltaV</quote>.  WebDAV/DeltaV clients and
        servers are often called just <quote>DeltaV</quote> programs,
        since DeltaV implies the existence of basic WebDAV.</para>

      <para>DeltaV introduces a whole slew of new acronyms, but don't
        be intimidated.  The ideas are fairly straightforward:</para>

      <variablelist>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Per-resource versioning</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Like CVS and other version-control systems,
              DeltaV assumes that each resource has a potentially
              infinite number of states.  A client begins by placing
              a resource under version control using the new
              <literal>VERSION-CONTROL</literal> method.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Server-side working-copy model</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Some DeltaV servers support the ability to create
              a virtual workspace on the server, where all of your
              work is performed.  Clients use the
              <literal>MKWORKSPACE</literal> method to create a
              private area, then indicate they want to change
              specific resources by <quote>checking them out</quote>
              into the workspace, editing them, and <quote>checking
              them in</quote> again.  In HTTP terms, the sequence of
              methods would be <literal>CHECKOUT</literal>,
              <literal>PUT</literal>,
              <literal>CHECKIN</literal>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Client-side working-copy model</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Some DeltaV servers also support the idea that the
              client may have a private working copy on local disk.
              When the client wants to commit changes to the server,
              it begins by creating a temporary server transaction
              (called an <firstterm>activity</firstterm>) with the
              <literal>MKACTIVITY</literal> method.  The client then
              performs a <literal>CHECKOUT</literal> on each
              resource it wishes to change and sends
              <literal>PUT</literal> requests.  Finally, the client
              performs a <literal>CHECKIN</literal> resource, or
              sends a <literal>MERGE</literal> request to check in
              all resources at once.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Configurations</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>DeltaV allows you define flexible collections of
              resources called <quote>configurations</quote>, which
              don't necessarily correspond to particular
              directories.  A configuration can be made to point to
              specific versions of files, and then a
              <quote>baseline</quote> snapshot can be made, much
              like a tag.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Extensibility</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>DeltaV defines a new method,
              <literal>REPORT</literal>, which allows the client and
              server to perform customized data exchanges.  While
              DeltaV defines a number of standardized history reports
              that a client can request, the server is also free
              to define custom reports.  The client sends a
              <literal>REPORT</literal> request with a
              properly-labeled XML body full of custom data; assuming
              the server understands the specific report-type, it
              responds with an equally custom XML body.  This
              technique is very similar to XML-RPC.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.webdav.svn-and-deltav">
    <title>Subversion and DeltaV</title>

    <para>The original WebDAV standard has been widely successful.
      Every modern computer operating system has a general WebDAV
      client built-in (details to follow), and a number of popular
      standalone applications are also able to speak WebDAV &mdash;
      Microsoft Office, Dreamweaver, and Photoshop to name a few.  On
      the server end, the Apache webserver has been able to provide
      WebDAV services since 1998 and is considered the de-facto
      open-source standard.  There are several other commercial WebDAV
      servers available, including Microsoft's own IIS.</para>

    <para>DeltaV, unfortunately, has not been so successful.  It's
      very difficult to find any DeltaV clients or servers.  The few
      that do exist are relatively unknown commercial products, and
      thus it's very difficult to test interoperability.  It's not
      entirely clear as to why DeltaV has remained stagnant.  Some
      argue that the specification is just too complex, others argue
      that while WebDAV's features have mass appeal (even the least
      technical users appreciate network file-sharing), version
      control features aren't interesting or necessary for most users.
      Finally, some have argued that DeltaV remains unpopular because
      there's still no open-source server product which implements
      it.</para>

    <para>When Subversion was still in its design phase, it seemed
      like a great idea to use Apache httpd as the main network
      server.  It already had a module to provide WebDAV services.
      DeltaV was a relatively new specification.  The hope was that
      the Subversion server module (mod_dav_svn) would eventually
      evolve into an open-source DeltaV reference implementation.
      Unfortunately, DeltaV has a very specific versioning model that
      doesn't quite line up with Subversion's model.  Some concepts
      were mappable, others were not.</para>

    <para>The upshot is that</para>

    <orderedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Subversion client is not a fully-implemented DeltaV
          client.</para>

        <para>The client needs certain things from the server that
          DeltaV cannot provide, and thus is largely dependent on a
          number of Subversion-specific <literal>REPORT</literal>
          requests that only mod_dav_svn understands.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>mod_dav_svn is not a fully-implemented DeltaV server.</para>

        <para>Many portions of the DeltaV specification were irrelevant to
          Subversion, and thus left unimplemented.</para>
      </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

    <para>There is still some debate in the developer community as to
      whether or not it's worthwhile to remedy either of these
      situations.  It's fairly unrealistic to change Subversion's
      design to match DeltaV, so there's probably no way the client
      can ever learn to get everything it needs from a general DeltaV
      server.  On the other hand,
      mod_dav_svn <emphasis>could</emphasis> be further developed to
      implement all of DeltaV, but it's hard to find motivation to do
      so&mdash;there are almost no DeltaV clients to interoperate
      with.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.webdav.autoversioning">
    <title>Autoversioning</title>

    <para>While the Subversion client is not a full DeltaV client, nor
      the Subversion server a full DeltaV server, there's still a
      glimmer of WebDAV interoperability to be happy about:  it's
      called autoversioning.</para>

    <para>Autoversioning is an optional feature defined in the DeltaV
      standard.  A typical DeltaV server will reject an ignorant
      WebDAV client attempting to do a <literal>PUT</literal> to a
      file that's under version control.  To change a
      version-controlled file, the server expects a series proper
      versioning requests: something like
      <literal>MKACTIVITY</literal>, <literal>CHECKOUT</literal>,
      <literal>PUT</literal>, <literal>CHECKIN</literal>.  But if the
      DeltaV server supports autoversioning, then write-requests from
      basic WebDAV clients are accepted.  The server behaves as if the
      client had issued the proper series of versioning requests,
      performing a commit under the hood.  In other words, it allows a
      DeltaV server to interoperate with ordinary WebDAV
      clients that don't understand versioning.</para>

    <para>Because so many operating systems already have integrated
      WebDAV clients, the use case for this feature borders on
      fantastical: imagine an office of ordinary users running
      Microsoft Windows or Mac OS.  Each user <quote>mounts</quote>
      the Subversion repository, which appears to be an ordinary
      network folder.  They use the shared folder as they always do:
      open files, edit them, save them.  Meanwhile, the server is
      automatically versioning everything.  Any administrator (or
      knowledgeable user) can still use a Subversion client to search
      history and retrieve older versions of data.</para>

    <para>This scenario isn't fiction: it's real and it works, as of
      Subversion 1.2 and later.  To activate autoversioning in
      mod_dav_svn, use the <literal>SVNAutoversioning</literal>
      directive within the <filename>httpd.conf</filename> Location
      block, like so:</para>

    <screen>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNPath /path/to/repository
  SVNAutoversioning on
&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

    <para>When SVNAutoversioning is active, write requests from WebDAV
      clients result in automatic commits.  A generic log message is
      auto-generated and attached to each revision.</para>

    <para>Before activating this feature, however, understand what
      you're getting into.  WebDAV clients tend to do
      <emphasis>many</emphasis> write requests, resulting in a huge
      number of automatically committed revisions.  For example, when
      saving data, many clients will do a <literal>PUT</literal> of a
      0-byte file (as a way of reserving a name) followed by another
      <literal>PUT</literal> with the real filedata.  The single
      file-write results in two separate commits.  Also consider that
      many applications auto-save every few minutes, resulting in even
      more commits.</para>

    <para>If you have a post-commit hook program that sends email, you
      may want to disable email generation either altogether, or on
      certain sections of the repository; it depends on whether you
      think the influx of emails will still prove to be valuable
      notifications or not.  Also, a smart post-commit hook program
      can distinguish between a transaction created via autoversioning
      and one created through a normal <command>svn commit</command>.
      The trick is to look for a revision property
      named <literal>svn:autoversioned</literal>.  If present, the
      commit was made by a generic WebDAV client.</para>

    <para>Another feature that may be a useful complement
      for <literal>SVNAutoversioning</literal> comes from
      Apache's <literal>mod_mime</literal> module.  If a generic
      WebDAV client adds a new file to the repository, there's no
      opportunity for the user to set the
      the <literal>svn:mime-type</literal> property.  This might cause
      the file to appear as <quote>generic</quote> icon when viewed
      within a WebDAV shared folder, not having an association with
      any application.  One remedy is to have a sysadmin (or other
      Subversion-knowledgable person) check out a working copy and
      manually set the <literal>svn:mime-type</literal> property on
      necessary files. But there's potentially no end to such cleanup
      tasks.  Instead, you can use
      the <literal>ModMimeUsePathInfo</literal> directive in
      your Subversion <literal>&lt;Location&gt;</literal>
      block:</para>
 
    <screen>
&lt;Location /repos&gt;
  DAV svn
  SVNPath /path/to/repository
  SVNAutoversioning on

  ModMimeUsePathInfo on

&lt;/Location&gt;
</screen>

    <para>This directive allows <literal>mod_mime</literal> to attempt
      automatic deduction of the mime-type on new files that enter the
      repository via autoversioning.  The module looks at the file's
      named extension and possibly the contents as well; if the file
      matches some common patterns, then the the
      file's <literal>svn;mime-type</literal> property will be set
      automatically.</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.webdav.clients">
    <title>Client Interoperability</title>

    <para>All WebDAV clients fall into one of three
      categories&mdash;standalone applications, file-explorer
      extensions, or filesystem implementations.  These categories
      broadly define the types of WebDAV functionality available to
      users.  <xref linkend="svn.webdav.clients.tbl-1"/> gives our
      categorization and a quick description of some common pieces of
      WebDAV-enabled software.  More details about these software
      offerings, as well as their general category, can be found in
      the sections that follow.</para>

    <table id="svn.webdav.clients.tbl-1">
      <title>Common WebDAV Clients</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Software</entry>
            <entry>Category</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Adobe Photoshop</entry>
            <entry>Standalone WebDAV applications</entry>
            <entry>Image editing software, allowing direct opening
              from, and writing to, WebDAV URLs</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cadaver</entry>
            <entry>Standalone WebDAV applications</entry>
            <entry>Command-line WebDAV client supporting file
              transfer, tree, and locking operations</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DAV Explorer</entry>
            <entry>Standalone WebDAV applications</entry>
            <entry>GUI tool for exploring WebDAV shares</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>davfs2</entry>
            <entry>WebDAV filesystem implementation</entry>
            <entry>Linux file system driver that allows you to mount a
              WebDAV share</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>GNOME Nautilus</entry>
            <entry>File-explorer WebDAV extensions</entry>
            <entry>GUI file explorer able to perform tree
              operations on a WebDAV share</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>KDE Konqueror</entry>
            <entry>File-explorer WebDAV extensions</entry>
            <entry>GUI file explorer able to perform tree
              operations on a WebDAV share</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Mac OS X</entry>
            <entry>WebDAV filesystem implementation</entry>
            <entry>Operating system with built-in support for mounting
              WebDAV shares locally</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Macromedia Dreamweaver</entry>
            <entry>Standalone WebDAV applications</entry>
            <entry>Web production software able to directly read from
              and write to WebDAV URLs</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Microsoft Office</entry>
            <entry>Standalone WebDAV applications</entry>
            <entry>Office productivity suite with several components
              able to directly read from and write to WebDAV
              URLs</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Microsoft Web Folders</entry>
            <entry>File-explorer WebDAV extensions</entry>
            <entry>GUI file explorer program able to perform tree
              operations on a WebDAV share</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Novell NetDrive</entry>
            <entry>WebDAV filesystem implementation</entry>
            <entry>Drive-mapping program for assigning Windows drive
              letters to a mounted remote WebDAV share</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>SRT WebDrive</entry>
            <entry>WebDAV filesystem implementation</entry>
            <entry>File transfer software which, among other things,
              allows the assignment of Windows drive letters to a
              mounted remote WebDAV share</entry>
          </row>

        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.webdav.clients.standalone">
      <title>Standalone WebDAV applications</title>

      <para>A WebDAV application is a program which contains built-in
        functionality for speaking WebDAV protocols with a WebDAV
        server.  We'll cover some of the most popular programs with
        this kind of WebDAV support.</para>

      <sect3 id="svn.webdav.clients.standalone.windows">
        <title>Microsoft Office, Dreamweaver, Photoshop</title> 
  
        <para>On Windows, there are several well-known applications
          that contain integrated WebDAV client functionality, such as
          Microsoft's Office,
          <footnote>
            <para>WebDAV support was removed from Microsoft Access for
              some reason, but exists in the rest of the Office
              suite.</para>
          </footnote>
          Adobe's Photoshop, and Macromedia's Dreamweaver programs.
          They're able to directly open and save to URLs, and tend to
          make heavy use of WebDAV locks when editing a file.</para>
  
        <para>Note that while many of these programs also exist for
          the Mac OS X, they do not appear to support WebDAV directly
          on that platform.  In fact, on Mac OS X, the
          <guimenu>File-&gt;Open</guimenu> dialog box doesn't allow
          one to type a path or URL at all.  It's likely that the
          WebDAV features were deliberately left out of Macintosh
          versions of these programs, since OS X already provides such
          excellent low-level filesystem support for WebDAV.</para>
  
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn.webdav.clients.standalone.free">
        <title>Cadaver, DAV Explorer</title>
  
        <para>Cadaver is a bare-bones Unix commandline program for
          browsing and changing WebDAV shares.  Like the Subversion
          client, it uses the neon HTTP library&mdash;not surprisingly,
          both neon and cadaver are written by the same author.  Cadaver
          is free software (GPL license) and is available at <ulink
          url="http://www.webdav.org/cadaver/"/>.</para>
  
        <para>Using cadaver is similar to using a commandline FTP
          program, and thus it's extremely useful for basic WebDAV
          debugging.  It can be used to upload or download files in a
          pinch, and also to examine properties, copy, move, lock or
          unlock files:</para>
        
        <screen>
$ cadaver http://host/repos
dav:/repos/&gt; ls
Listing collection `/repos/': succeeded.
Coll: &gt; foobar                                 0  May 10 16:19
      &gt; playwright.el                       2864  May  4 16:18
      &gt; proofbypoem.txt                     1461  May  5 15:09
      &gt; westcoast.jpg                      66737  May  5 15:09

dav:/repos/&gt; put README
Uploading README to `/repos/README':
Progress: [=============================&gt;] 100.0% of 357 bytes succeeded.

dav:/repos/&gt; get proofbypoem.txt
Downloading `/repos/proofbypoem.txt' to proofbypoem.txt:
Progress: [=============================&gt;] 100.0% of 1461 bytes succeeded.
</screen>

        <para>DAV Explorer is another standalone WebDAV client, written
          in Java.  It's under a free Apache-like license and is
          available at <ulink url="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~webdav/"/>.
          DAV Explorer does everything cadaver does, but has the
          advantages of being portable and being more user-friendly GUI
          application.  It's also one of the first clients to support
          the new WebDAV Access Control Protocol (RFC 3744).</para>
  
        <para>Of course, DAV Explorer's ACL support is useless in this
          case, since mod_dav_svn doesn't support it.  The fact that
          both Cadaver and DAV Explorer support some limited DeltaV
          commands isn't particularly useful either, since they don't
          allow <literal>MKACTIVITY</literal> requests.  But it's not
          relevant anyway; we're assuming all of these clients are
          operating against an autoversioning repository.</para>
  
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.webdav.clients.file-explorer-extensions">
      <title>File-explorer WebDAV extensions</title>

      <para>Some popular file explorer GUI programs support WebDAV
        extensions which allow a user to browse a DAV share as if it
        was just another directory on the local computer, and allowing
        basic tree editing operations on the items in that share.  For
        example, Windows Explorer is able to browse a WebDAV server as
        a <quote>network place</quote>.  Users can drag files to and
        from the desktop, or can rename, copy, or delete files in the
        usual way.  But because it's only a feature of the
        file-explorer, the DAV share isn't visible to ordinary
        applications.  All DAV interaction must happen through the
        explorer interface.</para>

      <sect3 id="svn.webdav.clients.file-explorer-extensions.windows">
        <title>Microsoft Web Folders</title> 
  
        <para>Microsoft was one of the original backers of the WebDAV
          specification, and first started shipping a client in Windows
          98, known as <quote>Web Folders</quote>.  This client was also
          shipped in Windows NT4 and 2000.</para>
  
        <para>The original Web Folders client was an extension to
          Explorer, the main GUI program used to browse filesystems.  It
          works well enough.  In Windows 98, the feature might need to
          be explicitly installed if Web Folders aren't already visible
          inside <quote>My Computer</quote>.  In Windows 2000, simply
          add a new <quote>network place</quote>, enter the URL, and the
          WebDAV share will pop up for browsing.</para>
  
        <para>With the release of Windows XP, Microsoft started shipping
          a new implementation of Web Folders, known as the <quote>WebDAV
          mini-redirector</quote>.  The new implementation is a
          filesystem-level client, allowing WebDAV shares to be mounted
          as drive letters.  Unfortunately, this implementation is
          incredibly buggy.  The client usually tries to convert http
          URLs (<literal>http://host/repos</literal>) into UNC share
          notation (<literal>\\host\repos</literal>); it also often
          tries to use Windows Domain authentication to respond to
          basic-auth HTTP challenges, sending usernames as
          <literal>HOST\username</literal>.  These interoperability
          problems are severe and documented in numerous places around
          the web, to the frustration of many users.  Even Greg Stein,
          the original author of Apache's WebDAV module, recommends
          against trying to use XP Web Folders against an Apache
          server.</para>
  
        <para>It turns out that the original
          <quote>Explorer-only</quote> Web Folders implementation isn't
          dead in XP, it's just buried.  It's still possible to find it
          by using this technique:</para>
  
        <orderedlist>
  
          <listitem>
            <para>Go to 'Network Places'.</para>
          </listitem>
  
          <listitem>
            <para>Add a new network place.</para>
          </listitem>
  
          <listitem>
            <para>When prompted, enter the URL of the repository, but
              <emphasis>include a port number</emphasis> in the URL.
              For example, <literal>http://host/repos</literal> would be
              entered as <literal>http://host:80/repos</literal> instead.
            </para>
          </listitem>
  
          <listitem>
            <para>Respond to any authentication prompts.</para>
          </listitem>
  
        </orderedlist>
  
        <para>There are a number of other rumored workarounds to the
          problems, but none of them seem to work on all versions and
          patchlevels of Windows XP.  In our tests, only the previous
          algorithm seems to work consistently on every system.  The
          general consensus of the WebDAV community is that you should
          avoid the new Web Folders implementation and use the old one
          instead, and that if you need real a real filesystem-level
          client for Windows XP, then use a third-party program like
          WebDrive or NetDrive.</para>

        <para>A final tip: if you're attempting to use XP Web Folders,
          make sure you have the absolute latest version from
          Microsoft.  For example, Microsoft released a bug-fixed
          version in January 2005, available at
          <ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/?kbid=892211"/>.
          In particular, this release is known to fix a bug whereby
          browsing a DAV share shows an unexpected infinite
          recursion.</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn.webdav.clients.file-explorer-extensions.linux-de">
        <title>Nautilus, Konqueror</title> 
  
        <para>Nautilus is the official file manager/browser for the
          GNOME desktop (<ulink url="http://www.gnome.org"/>), and
          Konqueror is the manager/browser for KDE desktop (<ulink
          url="http://www.kde.org"/>).  Both of these applications have
          an explorer-level WebDAV client built-in, and operate just
          fine against an autoversioning repository.</para>
  
        <para>In GNOME's Nautilus, from the <guimenu>File
          menu</guimenu>, select <guimenuitem>Open
          location</guimenuitem> and enter the URL.  The repository
          should then be displayed like any other filesystem.</para>
  
        <para>In KDE's Konqueror, you need to use the
          <literal>webdav://</literal> scheme when entering the URL in
          the location bar.  If you enter an <literal>http://</literal>
          URL, Konqueror will behave like an ordinary web browser.
          You'll likely see the generic HTML directory listing produced
          by mod_dav_svn.  By entering
          <literal>webdav://host/repos</literal> instead of
          <literal>http://host/repos</literal>, Konqueror becomes a
          WebDAV client and displays the repository as a
          filesystem.</para>
  
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="svn.webdav.clients.fs-impl">
      <title>WebDAV filesystem implementation</title>

      <para>The WebDAV filesystem implementation is arguably the best
        sort of WebDAV client.  It's implemented as a low-level
        filesystem module, typically within the operating system's
        kernel.  This means that the DAV share is mounted like any
        other network filesystem, similar to mounting an NFS share on
        Unix, or attaching an SMB share as drive-letter in Windows.
        As a result, this sort of client provides completely
        transparent read/write WebDAV access to all programs.
        Applications aren't even aware that WebDAV requests are
        happening.</para>

      <sect3 id="svn.webdav.clients.fs-impl.windows">
        <title>WebDrive, NetDrive</title> 
  
        <para>Both WebDrive and NetDrive are excellent commercial
          products which allows a WebDAV share to be attached as drive
          letters in Windows.  We've had nothing but success with
          these products.  At the time of writing, WebDrive can be
          purchased from South River Technologies (<ulink
          url="http://www.southrivertech.com"/>).  NetDrive ships with
          Netware, is free of charge, and can be found by searching
          the web for <quote>netdrive.exe</quote>.  Though it is
          freely available online, users are required to have a
          Netware license.  (If any of that sounds odd to you, you're
          not alone.  See this page on Novell's website: <ulink
          url="http://www.novell.com/coolsolutions/qna/999.html"/>)</para>
  
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn.webdav.clients.fs-impl.macosx">
        <title>Mac OS X</title> 

        <para>Apple's OS X operating system has an integrated
          filesystem-level WebDAV client.  From the Finder, select the
          <guimenuitem>Connect to Server</guimenuitem> item from the
          <guimenu>Go menu</guimenu>.  Enter a WebDAV URL, and it
          appears as a disk on the desktop, just like any other mounted
          volume.<footnote><para>From the Darwin terminal, one can also
          run <literal>mount -t webdav URL
          /mountpoint</literal></para></footnote>.</para>
  
        <para>Note that if your mod_dav_svn is older than version 1.2,
          OS X will refuse to mount the share as read-write; it will
          appear as read-only.  This is because the OS X insists on
          locking support for read-write shares, and the ability to lock
          files first appeared in Subversion 1.2.</para>
  
        <para>One more word of warning: OS X's WebDAV client can
          sometimes be overly sensitive to HTTP redirects.  If OS X is
          unable to mount the repository at all, you may need to enable
          the BrowserMatch directive in the Apache server's
          <filename>httpd.conf</filename>:</para>
  
        <screen>
BrowserMatch "^WebDAVFS/1.[012]" redirect-carefully
</screen>
  
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="svn.webdav.clients.fs-impl.linux">
        <title>Linux davfs2</title> 
  
        <para>Linux davfs2 is a filesystem module for the Linux kernel,
          whose development is located at <ulink
          url="http://dav.sourceforge.net/"/>.  Once installed, a WebDAV
          network share can be mounted with the usual Linux mount
          command:</para>
  
        <screen>
$ mount.davfs http://host/repos /mnt/dav
</screen>
  
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

</appendix>

<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "appendix")
end:
-->
